<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H003B00687B7C486389DA6F541FA3B95B" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 HR 5801 IH: Shutdown Fairness Act</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">119th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5801</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20251021">October 21, 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="J000301">Mr. Johnson of South Dakota</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="M001230">Mr. Mackenzie</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="W000829">Mr. Wied</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="B000740">Mrs. Bice</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="I000056">Mr. Issa</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="L000599">Mr. Lawler</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="M000871">Mr. Mann</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S001189">Mr. Austin Scott of Georgia</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="M001215">Mrs. Miller-Meeks</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HAP00">Committee on Appropriations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To appropriate funds for pay and allowances of excepted Federal employees for periods of work performed during a lapse in appropriations, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H5B1678ACA0EF4E04BA4EAB05FE57BB2D" style="OLC"> 
<section section-type="section-one" id="HBE0C0E6E14C646AE9360C617EC81AD50"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Shutdown Fairness Act</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HCFC44596368543D283CE283170125F62"><enum>2.</enum><header>Appropriations</header> <subsection id="H0DEADA9F02684EBF8E22A95266DB9751"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text>
<paragraph id="H7D0471D27B1C4B0B90E353579D1217D4"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <term>agency</term> means each authority of the executive, legislative, or judicial branch of the Government of the United States;</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="HAEC70A5A41EA41209B2E150D4EA2C359"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <term>excepted employee</term>—</text>
<subparagraph id="HE4712EF6AC714A2DBD6F16FED2F86DBE"><enum>(A)</enum><text>means an employee of an agency who the head of that agency determines is an excepted employee or an employee performing emergency work, as those terms are defined by the Office of Personnel Management; and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H27527BD2E7004C54AC0433E666ED8E71"><enum>(B)</enum><text>includes—</text>
<clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H729F48D6EFDB4B94A4E3B7ECF2B7CE08"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">a contractor who—</text> <subclause id="H20881E6D3E6C45EB9F122E472AB818A2"><enum>(I)</enum><text>provides support to an employee described in subparagraph (A); and</text></subclause>
<subclause id="HCE3B2D75F68E46C888E5F279B93AB7D4"><enum>(II)</enum><text>is required to perform work during a lapse in appropriations, as determined by the head of the agency with respect to which the contractor provides support; and</text></subclause></clause> <clause commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H43D06338EF0B4771A720A4BFC0BBE69E"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>a member of the Armed Forces on active duty; and</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph>
<paragraph commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="H0C768FF83A154BE88157E5B16E6C1ED7"><enum>(3)</enum><text>the term <term>excepted work</term> means work performed by an excepted employee during a period during which interim or full-year appropriations for the applicable fiscal year are not in effect for the applicable agency.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H3321AE1620A24403BE1391B850C0ECB8"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Appropriations</header><text>For fiscal year 2026, and any fiscal year thereafter, for any period during which interim continuing appropriations or full-year appropriations for that fiscal year are not in effect for an agency, there are appropriated to the head of the agency, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, such sums as are necessary to provide standard rates of pay, allowances, pay differentials, benefits, and other payments otherwise payable on a regular basis to excepted employees of the agency with respect to any period of excepted work performed by the excepted employees.</text></subsection>
<subsection id="HD31784B328C040319F31C40DC0BC7628"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Termination</header><text>Appropriations and funds made available and authority granted under subsection (b) shall be available to the head of an agency until whichever of the following first occurs:</text> <paragraph id="HC626AA3FFF03478C9C5E91CBE3C23A70"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The enactment into law of appropriations for the agency until the end of the applicable fiscal year (including a continuing appropriation) that provide amounts for the purposes for which amounts are made available under subsection (b).</text></paragraph>
<paragraph id="HE3236F4AFA514B95A1FFB365DC2B31D6"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The enactment into law of appropriations for the agency until the end of the applicable fiscal year (including a continuing appropriation) without any appropriation for such purposes.</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HD629E465A39E4D9D8C6014DDC5CCBB2A"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Interim continuing appropriations</header><text>Appropriations made available under subsection (b) may not be obligated by the head of an agency during any period during which continuing appropriations for the purposes for which amounts are made available under subsection (b) are in effect for the agency.</text></subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HABD8982EB603483683A24CD93760885F">
        <enum>(e)</enum>
        <header>Charging to full-Year appropriations</header>
 <text>Obligations or expenditures made by the head of an agency pursuant to subsection (b) shall be charged to the applicable appropriation for the agency whenever a regular appropriation bill or a measure making continuing appropriations until the end of the applicable fiscal year for the agency becomes law.</text>
      </subsection>
<subsection commented="no" display-inline="no-display-inline" id="HEFDB089A39E44A70A51C4614FB175646"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Retroactive effective date</header><text>This Act shall take effect as if enacted on September 30, 2025.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

