<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE resolution PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/res.dtd//EN" "res.dtd">
<resolution public-private="public" resolution-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" resolution-type="senate-resolution" star-print="no-star-print" slc-id="S1-HLA25908-L48-TY-506"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 SRES 460 IS: Recognizing the accomplishments of President Donald J. Trump and recommending that he be awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2026.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">III</distribution-code><congress display="yes">119th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num>S. RES. 460</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20251021">October 21, 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S373">Mr. Cassidy</sponsor> (for himself and <cosponsor name-id="S317">Mr. Barrasso</cosponsor>) submitted the following resolution; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSHR00">Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>RESOLUTION</legis-type><official-title display="yes">Recognizing the accomplishments of President Donald J. Trump and recommending that he be awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2026.</official-title></form><preamble><whereas><text>Whereas President Donald J. Trump has a legacy of bold action to save lives around the world;</text></whereas><whereas commented="no"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whereas President Trump acted swiftly to protect human life by launching Operation Warp Speed to mobilize the scientific might of the United States to combat a novel pathogen;</text></whereas><whereas commented="no"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whereas Operation Warp Speed created unprecedented public-private partnerships to develop, approve, and distribute medical products in under a year;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas the United States Government directly partnered with companies to underwrite clinical trials and manufacturing capacity and enter into advance purchase agreements;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas the actions of the United States Government gave companies the certainty needed to scale production at record speed, which would not have been feasible without United States investment and leadership;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas an estimated 1,600,000 hospitalizations and 235,000 deaths in the United States were averted in the first 10 months that the vaccine was available;</text></whereas><whereas commented="no"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whereas President Trump’s leadership saved approximately 14,400,000 lives globally; and</text></whereas><whereas commented="no"><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Whereas Operation Warp Speed saved roughly $1,150,000,000,000 in medical costs through late 2022: Now, therefore, be it</text></whereas></preamble><resolution-body><section id="S1" display-inline="yes-display-inline" section-type="undesignated-section"><text>That the Senate—</text><paragraph id="idc09f31e799884c3cb15f65fd53f41e4a"><enum>(1)</enum><text>recognizes President Donald J. Trump in bringing all available Federal resources to bear through Operation Warp Speed to counter a novel pathogen;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="iddc8b271521414394a437eb3259afe631"><enum>(2)</enum><text>commends President Trump for his steadfast commitment to partnering with the private sector to save lives, protect public health, and revitalize economies; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id1086b63b695440888524a34db8125602"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recommends that President Donald J. Trump be awarded the 2026 Nobel Peace Prize, in recognition of his accomplishments and legacy of saving lives.</text></paragraph></section></resolution-body></resolution> 

