<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="HA752B4760FDF475AA0355850CAFB5CAE" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 HR 5806 IH: Pre-Apprenticeship Wrap-around Support Services Fund Act of 2025</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">119th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5806</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20251021">October 21, 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S000510">Mr. Smith of Washington</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HED00">Committee on Education and Workforce</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To direct the Secretary of Labor to make grants to eligible applicants to provide stipends to individuals enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="HDD51628F160D4745A116B7EF93613CC1" style="OLC"> 
<section id="HAA570829D6024CA2858AAD095F440023" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Pre-Apprenticeship Wrap-around Support Services Fund Act of 2025</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="HDDBCE56F7FF84402A0C39EA57A5CF40F"><enum>2.</enum><header>Grants to provide stipends to individuals enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program</header> <subsection id="HD7DC743CD7684D699D543019FA0CAF54" commented="no"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The Secretary of Labor may make grants to eligible applicants to provide stipends to individuals enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program in accordance with the requirements under this Act.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="H43A587C79A3D4B82B82AEE4038F73D97"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Pre-Apprenticeship program defined</header><text>For purposes of this Act, the term <term>pre-apprenticeship program</term> means a program, initiative, or set of strategies that—</text> <paragraph id="HCA9C6CA9A85F472E9C1FBB1422B37589"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is designed to prepare individuals to enroll in a registered apprenticeship program, including preparing individuals with the skills and competencies necessary to succeed in such program; </text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB962280ACD964CDEA8DA4AC67FC30ACD"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">is carried out by an eligible applicant that has entered into a formal agreement with one or more sponsors of a registered apprenticeship program; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H61D24E42A6F54BF8A5D2D840C20D4D0F"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">includes—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H4C5DB3D5A3FE4AB9AE9D6E8269B4BA4B"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">theoretical education (including the use of curricula); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HEE71939A83F6444BAC2696C8722E80CB"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">training (including hands-on training)—</text> 
<clause id="HAF3C9EA3312F441480E16E72B2B471D5"><enum>(i)</enum><text>aligned with industry standards of a registered apprenticeship program; and</text></clause> <clause id="H1652A1D7078B49D7AFEF98EC76CCB437"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>that does not displace an employee where such training takes place.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H746D3AC8AD824E05ACD2A9AE220EB38E" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Application</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">To be eligible to receive a grant under this Act, an eligible applicant shall submit an application to the Secretary at such time, in such manner, and containing such information as the Secretary may require.</text></subsection> <subsection id="H5CBFC5E01FC04F5D8187FB30E76F75B5"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Grant requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each grantee shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="H71D316557DA04D9D9B29A754177C384C"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">establish primary indicators of performance with respect to individuals enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program, which shall include—</text> <subparagraph id="H6CAA551F2815407E89080E687003C8F7"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of such individuals who are enrolled in a registered apprenticeship program within 12 months after completing a pre-apprenticeship program;</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HC5B4B421B52E4B69AB7A8BC4187AE771"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the percentage of such individuals who are employed in the industry of the pre-apprenticeship program in which such individual was enrolled within 12 months after completing the pre-apprenticeship program;</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HAA1BD975AA214512A8766F6D35E1A2E4"><enum>(C)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the median earnings of such individuals who are enrolled in a registered apprenticeship program within 12 months after completing a pre-apprenticeship program; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HBD2E044700374C4CA97A7D6955616121"><enum>(D)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the percentage of such individuals who obtain a recognized postsecondary credential or a secondary school diploma (or the recognized equivalent of such diploma) while enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship or within one year after completing a pre-apprenticeship program; and</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HEF8E43EF83E843D698FF57B6CA0FD9D1"><enum>(2)</enum><text>on an annual basis, collect data with respect to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="H88294606339A4D14AC3EA45929F730FB"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">the primary indicators of performance under paragraph (1);</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H4434E90EAA2A4B079602F965423747A9"><enum>(B)</enum><text>the number of stipends provided through grants funds under this Act; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HE196B1909E924E11A53597AD3C07A07A"><enum>(C)</enum><text>the amount of each such stipend.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H927F7728FA534C0397BF1A37A0B2AC72"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Additional requirement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each grantee shall prioritize the provision of stipends to individuals enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program who are also individuals with a barrier to employment.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HBAEEC9E6A21F4FDDBB3057FDE60C7298"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Use of stipend</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Each grantee shall ensure that a stipend awarded pursuant to this section is used only to reimburse for—</text> <paragraph id="HE36E782D34B14C4EAA48B17CD302BA3A"><enum>(1)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">necessary transportation costs with respect to a pre-apprenticeship program, including vehicle mileage and public transportation costs;</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HF86AC03D322C46EFBBC5C1C7080D0B86"><enum>(2)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">lost hourly wages of an individual enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program, in the case that participation in such program causes a reduction of hours at the place of employment of such individual; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H5415152A77A245C4B83776879958897E"><enum>(3)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">financial costs of an individual enrolled in a pre-apprenticeship program with respect to obtaining industry-based certifications during the period of enrollment in such program.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HFA55563A5F7A4A22A01BB10571B6E432"><enum>(g)</enum><header>Report</header> 
<paragraph id="H661EA416BC3F466D88C707C1F515202A"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Report to Secretary</header><text>Not later than 1 year after receiving a grant under this Act, and annually thereafter, each grantee shall submit to the Secretary a report that includes the data collected pursuant to subsection (d)(2).</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H8D2C2FBD0C594EC2AD5EC451F3764053"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Report to congressional committees</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, and annually thereafter, the Secretary shall submit to the Committee on Education and Workforce of the House of Representatives and the Committee on Health, Education, Labor, and Pensions of the Senate a report on the progress and outcomes with respect to each grant awarded under this Act. </text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE7C604C862A547239C7DBD8009D3AF6D" commented="no"><enum>(h)</enum><header>Additional definitions</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In this Act:</text> <paragraph id="HF16781AD4FAE45D1BF82AA5E0E4CAC53"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Eligible applicant</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>eligible applicant</term> means an entity that currently operates or sponsors a pre-apprenticeship program, including a joint labor-management partnership, an industry partnership, a local educational agency, a secondary school, an area career and technical education school, a State board, a local board, or a community-based organization.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H82E6AA7B856A44E99DAED7A5CB24179D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Grantee</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>grantee</term> means an eligible applicant that receives a grant under this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H386D6F37AC314BE79DD48E531F32A804"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Individual with a barrier to employment</header><text>The term <term>individual with a barrier to employment</term> has the meaning given the term under section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H1BC27B18AA154D1F8A94165CB4F430B1"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Formal agreement</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>formal agreement</term> means an agreement between an eligible applicant and one or more sponsors of a registered apprenticeship program that includes the following:</text> <subparagraph id="HE9E99C5540EB4560B7995B678371E9F8"><enum>(A)</enum><text>Enables individuals who successfully complete a pre-apprenticeship program—</text> 
<clause id="H7E43B61BE7024466A92A0D92E4476EAA"><enum>(i)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to enter into a registered apprenticeship program (dependent on availability and whether such individual meets the qualifications of such program); and</text></clause> <clause id="HFA3FFFF8F542454EB651F7B1A51E2BAF"><enum>(ii)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">to earn credit toward a registered apprenticeship program.</text></clause></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H0737AE34F6D24EA5A5DD328BDC739182"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Provides for a sponsor to review and approve the training referred to in subsection (b)(3), on an annual basis.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="HDF6020EACF1049E99E5516723A03DDA4"><enum>(5)</enum><header>Recognized postsecondary credential</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>recognized postsecondary credential</term> has the meaning given the term under section 3 of the Workforce Innovation and Opportunity Act (<external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/3102">29 U.S.C. 3102</external-xref>).</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HCA8A136DB8A645D4B93460DCEF1D895E" commented="no"><enum>(6)</enum><header>Registered apprenticeship program</header><text>The term <term>registered apprenticeship program</term> means an apprenticeship program that—</text> <subparagraph id="H8859BF17C59147D0BABD1F815B564B64"><enum>(A)</enum><text>is registered with the Department of Labor pursuant to the Act of August 16, 1937 (commonly known as the <quote>National Apprenticeship Act</quote>; <external-xref legal-doc="usc" parsable-cite="usc/29/50">29 U.S.C. 50 et seq.</external-xref>), or is recognized by the Department of Labor as a State apprenticeship agency; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="H4954D5D88CF34069B895F0ABFA171F4C"><enum>(B)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">complies with the requirements of subpart A of part 29 and subpart A of part 30 of title 29, Code of Federal Regulations (or successor regulations).</text></subparagraph></paragraph> <paragraph id="H97E2661AAB604E8DACF52C8934297DC5" commented="no"><enum>(7)</enum><header>Secretary</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">The term <term>Secretary</term> means the Secretary of Labor.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H0E220C9D7A7E454F8AC29C777762D40A"><enum>(i)</enum><header>Authorization of appropriations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">There are authorized to be appropriated such sums as may be necessary to carry out this Act.</text></subsection></section> </legis-body></bill>

