<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE resolution PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/res.dtd//EN" "res.dtd">
<resolution public-private="public" resolution-stage="Introduced-in-Senate" resolution-type="senate-resolution" star-print="no-star-print" slc-id="S1-DAV25L16-LSS-NH-50T"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 SRES 459 IS: Honoring the strategic importance of the C5+1 diplomatic platform and recognizing the deepening partnership between the United States and the nations of Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, and Uzbekistan.</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">III</distribution-code><congress display="yes">119th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num>S. RES. 459</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20251021">October 21, 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S375">Mr. Daines</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S380">Mr. Peters</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S364">Mr. Murphy</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S433">Mr. McCormick</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S402">Ms. Rosen</cosponsor>) submitted the following resolution; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="SSFR00">Committee on Foreign Relations</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>RESOLUTION</legis-type><official-title display="yes">Honoring the strategic importance of the C5+1 diplomatic platform and recognizing the deepening partnership between the United States and the nations of Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, and Uzbekistan.</official-title></form><preamble><whereas><text>Whereas, in 1991, the United States established diplomatic relations with Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, and Uzbekistan following the dissolution of the Soviet Union;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas the Governments of Uzbekistan, Tajikistan, and Kyrgyzstan provided essential support to United States and NATO operations in Afghanistan through the Northern Distribution Network;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas, on November 1, 2015, the United States and the C5 launched the C5+1 platform, a regional mechanism for high-level dialogue and cooperation, supported by a permanent Secretariat since 2022;</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas the inaugural Summit agreed on partnerships to increase national and regional security, trade and economics, and energy and environmental issues; and</text></whereas><whereas><text>Whereas, in 2023, the first presidential-level C5+1 summit identified new opportunities for partnerships in energy security, counterterrorism, infrastructure, and critical mineral mining development: Now, therefore, be it</text></whereas></preamble><resolution-body><section id="S1" display-inline="yes-display-inline" section-type="undesignated-section"><text>That the Senate—</text><paragraph id="id3c697887a27f4a5c8f2647b83db52860"><enum>(1)</enum><text>affirms the strategic importance of the C5+1 platform in promoting regional sovereignty, stability, and shared security interests with the United States;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id2c132f2b16ff4a41933b350b9267bab2"><enum>(2)</enum><text>appreciates expanded cooperation on energy and critical minerals through transport corridor development;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7451ac537d694a05a37979b31e35cf5c"><enum>(3)</enum><text>recognizes the unwavering commitment of the Central Asian nations to counterterrorism coordination under the C5+1; and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id7997afd75aa4413db44b193544ebcaec"><enum>(4)</enum><text>hopes for a reduction in strategic trade barriers and increase in continued prosperity and friendship.</text></paragraph></section></resolution-body></resolution> 

