<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Placed-on-Calendar-Senate" dms-id="A1" public-private="public" slc-id="S1-GOE25832-70V-9H-C19"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 S3031 PCS: Keep America Flying Act of 2026</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. Senate</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-22</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">II</distribution-code><calendar>Calendar No. 205</calendar><congress>119th CONGRESS</congress><session>1st Session</session><legis-num>S. 3031</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE SENATE OF THE UNITED STATES</current-chamber><action><action-date date="20251022" legis-day="20251021">October 22 (legislative day, October 21), 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="S355">Mr. Cruz</sponsor> (for himself, <cosponsor name-id="S419">Mr. Mullin</cosponsor>, <cosponsor name-id="S378">Mr. Lankford</cosponsor>, and <cosponsor name-id="S383">Mr. Sullivan</cosponsor>) introduced the following bill; which was read the first time</action-desc></action><action><action-date date="20251022">October 22, 2025</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title>Making continuing appropriations for essential Federal Aviation Administration and Transportation Security Administration pay and operations in the event of a Federal Government shutdown, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body><section id="S1" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Keep America Flying Act of 2026</short-title></quote>.</text></section><section id="id510adb5b40a947d9a4dc2c1162942851"><enum>2.</enum><header>Continuing appropriations for air traffic controllers and transportation security personnel</header><subsection id="id5125853ef18b44c987c2a0d273f33b4a"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>There are hereby appropriated for fiscal year 2026, out of any money in the Treasury not otherwise appropriated, for the period beginning October 1, 2025, during which interim or full-year appropriations for fiscal year 2026 are not in effect—</text><paragraph id="id83f64d99cfcf4f25a9ef12828cb38607"><enum>(1)</enum><text>such sums as are necessary to provide standard rates of pay, allowances, pay differentials, benefits, and other payments otherwise payable on a regular basis to air traffic controllers and other essential operational personnel of the Federal Aviation Administration whose services are required for the safe and orderly operation of the national airspace system;</text></paragraph><paragraph id="ideab50e0b97324e8abbbc8152d61ba6b3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>such sums as are necessary to provide standard rates of pay, allowances, pay differentials, benefits, and other payments otherwise payable on a regular basis to employees of the Transportation Security Administration engaged in screening operations, aviation security duties, or related mission-support functions necessary to carry out security screening under <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/49/449">chapter 449</external-xref> of title 49, United States Code; </text></paragraph><paragraph id="id6b21c4484a1b4aa1991b7a04deb02b0a"><enum>(3)</enum><text>such sums as are necessary to provide for payments to contractors of the Federal Aviation Administration whom the Secretary of Transportation determines are providing support to the personnel described in paragraph (1); and</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4b8f998f647e4641944686a96978057e"><enum>(4)</enum><text>such sums as are necessary to provide for payments to contractors of the Transportation Security Administration whom the Administrator or Acting Administrator of the Transportation Security Administration determines are providing support to the personnel described in paragraph (2).</text></paragraph></subsection><subsection id="id7e02f82c164e449baf46cc107cea2f29"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Charge to future appropriations</header><text>Expenditures made pursuant to subsection (a) shall be charged to the applicable appropriation, fund, or authorization whenever an Act in which such applicable appropriation, fund, or authorization is included is enacted into law.</text></subsection></section><section id="id5ab8b85a98aa4674aa1c1e6ea3545713"><enum>3.</enum><header>Termination</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">Appropriations and funds made available and authority granted pursuant to this Act shall be available until whichever of the following first occurs:</text><paragraph id="idb48ef5447de64b03888ae80d86623197"><enum>(1)</enum><text>The enactment into law of an appropriation (including a continuing appropriation) for any purpose for which amounts are made available in section 2.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id5f08afd934d34851ba910b825d359a12"><enum>(2)</enum><text>The enactment into law of the applicable regular or continuing appropriations resolution or other Act without any appropriation for such purpose.</text></paragraph><paragraph id="id4d398fb5fff44507a7e209f902ef3938"><enum>(3)</enum><text>September 30, 2026.</text></paragraph></section><section id="id417ba462fc0748e3ad5c665c4abed934"><enum>4.</enum><header>Retroactive effective date</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act shall take effect as if enacted on September 30, 2025.</text></section></legis-body><endorsement><action-date date="20251022">October 22, 2025</action-date><action-desc>Read the second time and placed on the calendar</action-desc></endorsement></bill> 

