<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="billres.xsl"?>
<!DOCTYPE bill PUBLIC "-//US Congress//DTDs/bill.dtd//EN" "bill.dtd">
<bill bill-stage="Introduced-in-House" dms-id="H6CDD10224C0A4EB68AFD8938DEA0182E" public-private="public" key="H" bill-type="olc"><metadata xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">
<dublinCore>
<dc:title>119 HR 5810 IH: Federal Supervisor Education Act of 2025</dc:title>
<dc:publisher>U.S. House of Representatives</dc:publisher>
<dc:date>2025-10-21</dc:date>
<dc:format>text/xml</dc:format>
<dc:language>EN</dc:language>
<dc:rights>Pursuant to Title 17 Section 105 of the United States Code, this file is not subject to copyright protection and is in the public domain.</dc:rights>
</dublinCore>
</metadata>
<form>
<distribution-code display="yes">I</distribution-code><congress display="yes">119th CONGRESS</congress><session display="yes">1st Session</session><legis-num display="yes">H. R. 5810</legis-num><current-chamber>IN THE HOUSE OF REPRESENTATIVES</current-chamber><action display="yes"><action-date date="20251021">October 21, 2025</action-date><action-desc><sponsor name-id="T000480">Mr. Timmons</sponsor> introduced the following bill; which was referred to the <committee-name committee-id="HGO00">Committee on Oversight and Government Reform</committee-name></action-desc></action><legis-type>A BILL</legis-type><official-title display="yes">To provide for mandatory training for Federal Government supervisors and the assessment of management competencies, and for other purposes.</official-title></form><legis-body id="H78C3BA35E6A84E03A8F60A147A14149A" style="OLC"> 
<section id="H4E016A62310346DFBD75905475EB8F62" section-type="section-one"><enum>1.</enum><header>Short title</header><text display-inline="no-display-inline">This Act may be cited as the <quote><short-title>Federal Supervisor Education Act of 2025</short-title></quote>.</text></section> <section id="H394E11EE647D42C4B5D6DEF23C4ED02C"><enum>2.</enum><header>Mandatory training programs for supervisors</header> <subsection id="H50228B1A15B64E84A9DAE1EABA1CA654"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Section 4121 of title 5, United States Code, is amended to read as follows:</text> 
<quoted-block id="HED7C1DFA3ACF4C339DF1E026F3D234F4" style="USC"> 
<section id="HE9B26FA44F9E44DDA2E2E731B9F60D74"><enum>4121.</enum><header>Specific training programs</header> 
<subsection id="H01CD67CD3A0C4C26970B1A3946D5FEAE"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definitions</header><text>In this section—</text> <paragraph id="HAE8D5E3E17A54278A169733479E4D2D5"><enum>(1)</enum><text>the term <quote>program</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 1122(a)(1)(C) of title 31; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H34CBF11EEB7641DC832C6D62A5FD5697"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the term <quote>supervisor</quote> means—</text> <subparagraph id="H67C624B4F57F47F1854FF6F1AFFEB988"><enum>(A)</enum><text>a supervisor (as that term is defined in section 7103(a)(10));</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HA7BF1EEBFDA645888FC71FC73393FABE"><enum>(B)</enum><text>a management official (as that term is defined under such section); or</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H47938285094245A289049E5AEB367636"><enum>(C)</enum><text>any other employee as the Director of the Office of Personnel Management may by regulation prescribe.</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H69C41CF207294485ABE68EBC4CD1DB44"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Establishment of training programs</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">In consultation with the Office of Personnel Management, the head of each agency shall establish—</text> <paragraph id="H0D04EA86524D4E1F9AFC509DCF5E623A"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a comprehensive management succession program to provide training to employees to develop managers for the agency; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H30A007F414664FC898A0012192C874F0"><enum>(2)</enum><text>a program—</text> <subparagraph id="H0AB26F8F80C64AF5AE1353AC5DD17741" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">under which supervisors have individual development plans, established by the head, that provide for training on actions, options, and strategies a supervisor may use in—</text> 
<clause id="H8625C8FD411446A8847ECAC569978582" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>developing and discussing relevant performance goals and objectives with the employee and ensuring the performance goals and objectives align to the mission and priority goals of the agency;</text></clause> <clause id="H90FD2BB76B8C43E2B1AE7833AD0E8DD6" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>communicating and discussing progress relative to performance goals and objectives, and conducting performance appraisals;</text></clause> 
<clause id="HCF12E151635F40A0B7FA7F0D4EFCE84C" commented="no"><enum>(iii)</enum><text>mentoring and coaching employees and improving employee engagement, performance, and productivity;</text></clause> <clause id="H63BE544FBC6246DA9252C64646B96AB0" commented="no"><enum>(iv)</enum><text>fostering a work environment characterized by fairness, respect, equal opportunity, and attention paid to the merit of the work of employees;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H9C50009E72214F48BCA89574FB7FA13A" commented="no"><enum>(v)</enum><text>effectively managing employees with unacceptable performance, including training to understand the disciplinary options and procedures available to the supervisor;</text></clause> <clause id="HB52D12C479D04F85960A1A080F76DF4C" commented="no"><enum>(vi)</enum><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">effectively using the probationary period to examine whether an employee has demonstrated successful performance or conduct to continue past the probationary period, and to assess the needs and interests of the agency with respect to the probationary employee’s final appointment;</text></clause> 
<clause id="H2F91BF07630246929A5E6C35E18A0E96" commented="no"><enum>(vii)</enum><text>addressing reports of a hostile work environment, retaliation, or harassment of, or by, another supervisor or employee;</text></clause> <clause id="H80374CB420AB4857AEE0DC5807DC8B90" commented="no"><enum>(viii)</enum><text>meeting supervisor competencies established by the Office of Personnel Management or the employing agency of the supervisor; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HF46903064FD64578952D3230D58D42B8" commented="no"><enum>(ix)</enum><text>collaborating with human resources employees to recruit, select, appraise, and reward employees to build a workforce based on organizational goals, budget considerations, and staffing needs;</text></clause> </subparagraph> <subparagraph id="HF66EE33A810F4710852D784AD224C79C" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><text>to provide training to supervisors on the prohibited personnel practices under section 2302, employee rights, and the procedures and processes used to enforce employee rights; and</text></subparagraph> 
<subparagraph id="HEC8AD6F73B1C4149BDF73327262EF9C8" commented="no"><enum>(C)</enum><text>under which experienced supervisor mentors are identified, evaluated, and approved to provide guidance and advice to new or underperforming supervisors to—</text> <clause id="H6B37E3B316DB46249196C7E0ECF01545" commented="no"><enum>(i)</enum><text>transfer knowledge and advice in areas such as communication, critical thinking, responsibility, flexibility, motivating and engaging employees, teamwork, leadership, and professional development; and</text></clause> 
<clause id="HFEA3F8C75D4743A88F02DC548E019C25" commented="no"><enum>(ii)</enum><text>identify strengths and areas for development.</text></clause></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="H44091BB0E09F495BB99C86EE9A1BB6DE" commented="no"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Requirements for training design</header><text>Training in the program components established under subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (b)(2) shall—</text> 
<paragraph id="HDDF731C76E1F4E3DBDBB8A97D3D99C90" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>be designed using principles of adult learning and an industry standard instructional design model; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H17E6F0FA6F854DCD90FF708AB5DE2DE2" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>to the extent practicable, as determined by the agency, be training that is instructor-based.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H2B57BB7EE0514896A21EE648DDDC5AF1" commented="no"><enum>(d)</enum><header>Timing of training</header> 
<paragraph id="HECA41A005ABB4A2495C499B2E409D3DE" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Initial training</header> 
<subparagraph id="HAE0E69017AE44FEBAC756C3912AD980A" commented="no"><enum>(A)</enum><header>In general</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date an individual is appointed to the position of supervisor, such individual shall be required to have completed each program component established under subsection (b)(2).</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H2228EE7EEE064F9CBEA0DDA4125D071B" commented="no"><enum>(B)</enum><header>Extensions</header><text>The Director of the Office of Personnel Management may establish and administer procedures under which an agency may extend the 1-year period described under subparagraph (A) with respect to an individual.</text></subparagraph></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H5485CADC6F6D4E89A6B26B94E9A6BD94" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Subsequent training</header><text>After completion of a program component under subparagraphs (A) and (B) of subsection (b)(2), each supervisor shall be required to complete each program component under such subparagraphs not less frequently than once every 3 years.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6AC0EDDA95FF4270A30AEDDB3E919A5E" commented="no"><enum>(3)</enum><header>Credit for similar training</header><text>Each program component established under subsection (b)(2) shall include provisions under which the agency gives a supervisor credit toward a period of training that the agency determines is similar to training that the supervisor previously completed.</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="HB38061C58D124097A07F67DBA7C5AE7F" commented="no"><enum>(4)</enum><header>Effectiveness evaluation</header><text>Each agency shall measure the effectiveness of training program components established under subsection (b)(2).</text></paragraph></subsection> <subsection id="HE13090C760014842A582AF1B78D57492" commented="no"><enum>(e)</enum><header>Information on developmental opportunities</header><text>An agency shall make available, in a manner that may be determined by the Director of the Office of Personnel Management, to each supervisor—</text> 
<paragraph id="H6DAEC900535A4F3DA0F7BAD3B84FE9C1" commented="no"><enum>(1)</enum><text>a detailed list of developmental opportunities available to the supervisor; and</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H6E35ECC6E1A84A2D8819D41008D1E26A" commented="no"><enum>(2)</enum><text>the policies of the agency for requiring supervisor development.</text></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H985C5EB53A964196A209875C1D0590CD" commented="no"><enum>(f)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text display-inline="yes-display-inline">Not later than 1 year after the date of enactment of the Federal Supervisor Education Act of 2025, and notwithstanding section 4118(c), the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall prescribe regulations to carry out this section, including the monitoring of agency compliance with this section. Regulations prescribed under this subsection shall include measures by which to assess the effectiveness of agency supervisor training programs.</text></subsection> </section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block> </subsection> <subsection id="H7854B73E136C4CCA82DA41230822B694"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Regulations</header><text>Not later than 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act, the Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall prescribe regulations under section 4121(f) of title 5, United States Code, as amended by subsection (a) of this section.</text></subsection> 
<subsection id="HE2EE3CEDDE794DEBB0DC8C73B7E7754C"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Effective date and application</header> 
<paragraph id="H3F123A6DEF87470CB5837553C462DC5F"><enum>(1)</enum><header>In general</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall take effect 1 year after the date of the enactment of this Act.</text></paragraph> <paragraph id="H36B9A63A6FD4405D8BFB0B622717EA9D"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Applicability</header><text>The amendments made by this section shall apply to—</text> 
<subparagraph id="HF42E5F3327CE4618B8B7A8D3362BA0AB"><enum>(A)</enum><text>each individual appointed to the position of a supervisor (as that term is defined in section 4121(a) of title 5, United States Code, as added by subsection (a) of this section) on or after the effective date in paragraph (1); and</text></subparagraph> <subparagraph id="H0DABF17DE893469B928509DD882B93B5"><enum>(B)</enum><text>each individual who is employed in the position of a supervisor on the effective date in paragraph (1).</text></subparagraph></paragraph></subsection></section> 
<section id="HCE9B17F76072404C946CBE293454DA42"><enum>3.</enum><header>Management competencies</header> 
<subsection id="HF1924293E5284FB3B5993FCBA86FDA5F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>In general</header><text><external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/43">Chapter 43</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended—</text> <paragraph id="H8C10F18BCB6D47B0AE226466CEBF7E40"><enum>(1)</enum><text>by redesignating section 4305 as section 4306; and</text></paragraph> 
<paragraph id="H667B737E58204F22A794AA06385FADE3"><enum>(2)</enum><text>by inserting after section 4304 the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HE70F10CE59C7423E813EF586AEF73FC6" style="USC"> <section id="HBAB00316E6144F93B7908C82B4C8B2C2"><enum>4305.</enum><header>Management competencies</header> <subsection id="HCF5046A0257E46D1A93F284007A5F63F"><enum>(a)</enum><header>Definition</header><text>In this section, the term <quote>supervisor</quote> has the meaning given that term in section 4121(a).</text> </subsection> 
<subsection id="H7841A44BB1D44B8F90F533C928666321"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Guidance</header><text>The Director of the Office of Personnel Management shall issue guidance to agencies on competencies supervisors are expected to meet in order to effectively manage, and be accountable for managing, the performance of employees to fulfill the organizational goals and mission of the agency.</text></subsection> <subsection id="HA437BFF7D22B4A1A9E2D98540EA5D47E"><enum>(c)</enum><header>Assessment by agencies</header><text>Based on guidance issued under subsection (b) and on any additional competencies developed by an agency, each agency shall assess the performance of the supervisors and the overall capacity of the supervisors in that agency.</text></subsection></section><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph></subsection> 
<subsection id="H7D03D6D46F6D42B0BC48B0A90FCC4E45"><enum>(b)</enum><header>Technical and conforming amendments</header> 
<paragraph id="H7FE8E97F1EDC4BFC83BDE79A21CC18DA"><enum>(1)</enum><header>Table of sections</header><text>The table of sections for <external-xref legal-doc="usc-chapter" parsable-cite="usc-chapter/5/43">chapter 43</external-xref> of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking the item relating to section 4305 and inserting the following:</text> <quoted-block id="HD8DA79ED6DDA4CF9891658C358E9A067" style="USC"> <toc regeneration="no-regeneration"> <toc-entry level="section">4305. Management competencies.</toc-entry> <toc-entry level="section">4306. Regulations.</toc-entry></toc><after-quoted-block>.</after-quoted-block></quoted-block></paragraph> <paragraph id="H7CFF73874966409CB1239734A5280346"><enum>(2)</enum><header>Reference</header><text>Section 4304(b)(3) of title 5, United States Code, is amended by striking <quote>section 4305</quote> and inserting <quote>section 4306</quote>.</text></paragraph></subsection></section> 
</legis-body></bill>

